All right. Now that we've talked about
data types, how to convert between them,
how to tell what type of variable you
have, we are going to talk more in depth
about strings specifically. This is one
of my favorite parts of the course
because if you can manipulate a string,
you can make a computer do just about
anything that you want. So, let's get
started. The first thing you want to
know about strings is how to concatenate
them. So concatenation is where you take
one string and you glue it to another
string to create a whole new string. So
let's demonstrate that real quick. So I
could say come here in my code and
create a new variable. We'll say let to
create the new variable. Then we'll give
the variable name. We'll call it first
name and we'll say equals and then let's
just prompt the user for their first
name. So we'll say prompt and we'll say
what is your first name and we'll put a
semicolon.
Now, we also know that we could use the
alert function to share a message to the
screen. So, we could say hello world,
but hello world isn't the most
personalized message really. We want to
say hello and then whatever first name
they entered. So, what we're going to do
is I'm going to show you how to
concatenate. So, we're going to say
hello and then plus. And that says we
are now concatenating. Take the string
before the plus and the string after the
plus and glue them together. We know
that first name is a variable and the
variable it's holding is the result of
the prompt and that result is always a
string. So we know first name is a
string. So we can take the string hello
and concatenate it with the string
inside of first name. If we save our
code and we move over to our web
browser, we can see it says what is your
first name? I will enter toa. Hit okay
and it says hello toa. And you'll notice
it glued them directly to each other.
There's no space in between the hello
and the toa. Um, that's because
JavaScript's not smart enough. It
doesn't read English. All it knows is
you told it glue this string to this
string. And it did that. If you want a
space, you've got to tell it you want a
space. So, let's go back over and we'll
put that in. So, we'll say hello and
then we'll put a space and then we'll
concatenate on first name. So, you'll
notice the space is inside of the
quotes. So, it's part of this first
string. This first string is hello
space. and then we put a plus sign for
concatenation and then we put first name
and that glues them together and it says
hello and then whatever the first name
is. If we save this and we come over to
our code um I'm going to hit cancel and
reload the page um says what is your
first name? If we put Ryan and hit okay
it says hello space Ryan. And so we've
successfully concatenated. So let's come
back over to our code. We now know that
we can glue strings together. Let's say
we wanted to glue some complicated stuff
together. So, let's say we wanted to get
their last name and we'd say prompt,
what is your last name?
And then we want their GPA. GPA equals
prompt, what is your GPA?
And then you you get the picture. You
could get a lot of information and you
would need to concatenate it all
together. So I might be saying hello
last name, first name. Your GPA is and
then concatenating on the GPA. If we do
it the way I showed you originally, then
we'd have to say hello space last name
and then concatenate on a comma and then
concatenate on the first name and then
concatenate on a space and then the text
your GPA is and then a space and then
concatenate on the GPA. And you can see
that the more information you're
concatenating together, the more
complicated this becomes. So if we save
this and we come over, says, what is
your first name? Say Tim. What is your
last name? Drake. What is your GPA? 3.4.
And now it says, hello, Drake, Tim. Your
GPA is 3.4.
So that's great. We're only
concatenating three pieces of
information, but you could see how this
could quickly become a pain. So, I'm
going to hit close and I'm going to come
back over and I'm going to show you how
you could do this exact same thing a
little more simply. So, what I'm going
to do is I'm going to type alert and
then I'm going to create a string. And
what I'm going to create is called a
formatted string. The way you create a
formatted string is you use the little
back tick icon and it is right
underneath the escape key on your
computer. So, type the back tick icon
and then type it again and that will
give you a string. And inside of here,
we're going to say hello. And then now,
this is where we would want to inject
their last name. So, what we're going to
do is we're going to say dollar sign
curly braces.
Um, the curly braces are near the delete
or backspace key, depending on if you're
on Windows or Mac. It's directly below
it. Well, almost directly below it. So,
now anything I type in between these
curly braces, I can now reference other
variables. And JavaScript is smart
enough that it'll take this string and
it'll inject the variable directly in
there. So I can say hello last name
and then I can put a comma after the
curly braces and then I can put a dollar
sign and another set of curly braces.
First name and then I can put a space
and say your GPA is and then I can put
dollar sign curly braces GPA.
This line does exactly the same thing as
the line above, but now we don't have as
many plus signs and we don't have to
worry if we've closed all our double
quotes and make sure we have spaces in
all the right place. We can type out our
messages exactly as we want it to
appear. Put in placeholders and say what
we want to go into those placeholders.
So in this case, we have a placeholder
here and we want to fill it with
whatever last name is. A placeholder
whatever first name is. And a
placeholder here and we want to fill it
with whether whatever GPA is. These two
lines accomplish the exact same thing.
The second line, depending on your
opinion, might be more readable. In the
course, I don't care which one you do.
Just pick one and do whichever one works
for you. But these are two different
ways to concatenate the same thing. To
prove that to you, I will save this
code. We'll come over here and it'll
say, "What is your first name?" Tim.
What is your last name? Drake. What is
your GPA? 4.0. And it says, "Hello,
Drake, Tim. Your GPA is 4.0. 0. Hello
Drake, Tim, your GPA is 4.0. So, we got
two messages. They look exactly the
same. We were able to accomplish the
same thing. One of them uses um
formatted strings and the other one uses
concatenation. And I will let you take
your pick which one you prefer. Thanks
for watching.